<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Aden Dreams Of Blogging</title>
    <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="http://AdenJ86.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>It's simple. It's easy to use. It's a Jekyll theme.</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2016 15:03:11 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2016 15:03:11 -0500</lastBuildDate>

    
      <item>
        <title>New Partner</title>
        <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io/blog/2016-03-02/New-Partner.html</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Aigars Dzerviniks</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&quot;http://davidlnowak.github.io/blog/2016-03-02/post-week7-coding.html&quot;&gt;David&lt;/a&gt; both wrote in his blog post, working with a different lab partner last Thursday was tremendously helpful for me. Originally, I somewhat rudely tried to steal David from Todd, and normally I would work with David, Kelly, Diana, or Todd outside of class. I hadn’t worked with Hassan before, and I was pleasantly surprised to find that there were some aspects of coding that I understood a little better than him and could explain to him and there were other aspects of coding that he understood better and could clarify to me. This was helpful for me to see and experience because I realized that I am learning some of the concepts enough to explain them to other students and I’m not the only person who is not caught up on all the concepts or dailies. Hassan was also very honest that he really wanted us to figure out Bouncing Ball and Hud on our own even though our not getting very far on either project was frustrating for him. I could and can relate to both those sentiments: earnestly wanting to work hard and learn to do something on my own while also being discouraged when doing so doesn’t lead to a solved problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of the dailies, I’m almost caught up on them, which has assuaged my fear that I would be scrambling to finish them at the end of the semester, but I’m also frustrated that learning to code is still a slow process for me. Today, I watched the first three of the Daniel Schiffman videos that Scott posted for the original coding lesson. Schiffman’s videos were very helpful, and while I had watched some of them in the first few weeks of class I wish I had watched them from the beginning and in the order that Scott had posted them. I think this would have helped me grasp the coding ideas and practices a little faster. This is why it’s important not to fall behind, and to do all aspects of a course’s work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>keywords</title>
        <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io/blog/2016-03-02/Keywords.html</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Mar 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Aigars Dzerviniks</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Something that came to mind more than once as I read Alexander Galloway’s “Networks” and Protocol: How Control Exists after Decentralization is how changes in technology can change the meaning of words. In the same way that Raymond Williams traced the evolving definitions of certain words in Keywords, Galloway also notes words that have changed with advances in technology and tech’s rise in ubiquity. As &lt;a href=&quot;http://kellypolasek.github.io/blog/2016-03-02/power-and-control-blog.html&quot;&gt;Kelly&lt;/a&gt; mentioned, “Networks” comes from “Critical Terms for Media Studies”, which I’d assume builds off the strategy of Keywords. In “Networks”, Galloway notes that network “is a compound formed from the Old Saxon words net, an open-weave fabric used for catching or confining animals or objects, and werk, both an act of doing and the structure or thing resulting from the act” (283) while for “media studies the term appears most often in analyses of communications technologies” (283). Today, it is so easy to think of networks mainly related to technology and communication: the Internet, social networks, “to network”, etc. As Galloway notes, network is applicable to “material and industrial systems” and “the biological and life sciences” (283), among other fields and systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protocol is another word that has had its meanings and assumptions morph alongside changes in technology. In Protocol, Galloway writes, “Prior to its usage in computing, protocol referred to any type of correct or proper behavior within a specific system of conventions” (7). He also notes that protocol used to have a definitional bearing related to etiquette. Technology, specifically digital computing, has changed the meaning of protocol. According to Galloway, “Now, protocols refer specifically to standards governing the implementation of specific technologies” (7). Before reading Galloway, I had assumed that protocol’s meaning was strictly based in the realm of security measures. While protocol is part of security measures as Galloway notes in his description of protocols against nuclear attacks, the word originally had a more diplomatic or social meaning before the rise of digital computing. All of this is to say that not only can technology change us as users (per Marshall McLuhan), it can also affect our semantics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Surveillance And Neoliberalism</title>
        <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io/blog/2016-02-24/Surveillance-And-Neoliberalism.html</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Aigars Dzerviniks</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Scott mentioned last week in our discussion of Lev Manovich’s The Language of New Media that new media describes functions of itself under the regime of neoliberalism, and that this is less about technological capacity and more about operations of economic contexts. In her blog post for last week, &lt;a href=&quot;http://kellypolasek.github.io/blog/2016-02-17/fourth-reading-blog.html&quot;&gt;Kelly&lt;/a&gt; also astutely saw the connection between Manovich and books on neoliberalism by Wendey Brown and David Harvey. The ways that neoliberalism is bolstered by technology also came up in our class discussion of Donna Haraway, and the intersection between technology and neoliberalism comes up again in Wendy Hui Kyong Chun’s Programmed Visions: Software Memory. In her introduction, Chun writes, “computers in the period this book focuses on (post-World War II) coincide with the emergence of neoliberalism” (7) and she goes on to describe David Harvey’s very clear formulation of neoliberalism as being a social order where economic policies are prioritized around freedom in the market and de-regulation rather than social democratic values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chun argues that our dependence on computers groom us for greater indebtedness to neoliberalism: “By individuating us and also integrating us into a totality, their interfaces offer us a form of mapping, of storing files central to our seemingly sovereign-empowered-subjectivity” (9). She goes to mention how data-mining further contributes to this mapping. Data-mining isn’t a brand new trend, but the ubiquity of computers, internet use, smartphones, and social media have made data-mining more common, powerful, and invasive. Chun asks the great question “Who needs surveillance when you constantly document your life?” (page unnumbered). This seems to connect to Manovich’s emphasis on the database, and a social network like Facebook can easily be considered a database where the sovereign corporation The Facebook may theoretically have access to all its users’ branches of information. In his Spaces of Global Capitalism: Towards a Theory of Uneven Geographical Development, Harvey notes that with neoliberalism’s rise “surveillance and policing multiply” (26). Chun also describes the ways that Google and cable companies survey their users in this high-tech neoliberal world. Like Scott mentioned in class, neoliberalism’s meaning can be slippery and can have different definitions, but I think that paying attention to how technology supports neoliberalism and vice versa seems important for both this class and thinking about neoliberalism in general.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Oy Vey Coding</title>
        <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io/blog/2016-02-24/Oy-Vey-Coding.html</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Aigars Dzerviniks</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent an obscene amount of time coding in the past week: an hour and a half during last Thursday’s open lab, five hours last Friday as Todd and then David worked with me on Keyed Up Ball, two hours at Monday’s open lab, and five and a half hours today as a I coded by myself, then with Kelly and Diana, and finally with Scott. So I’ve coded fourteen hours (!) outside of class in the past week. For brevity’s sake I will keep this post limited to today’s coding. I realized last week how behind I am on understanding this course’s concepts, and I am also behind on submitting my dailies (I still have three dailies from week three to finish) so I’ve been making even more of an effort to code more and specifically code more on my own. Today I messed around with my falling rain daily for two hours, making changes in the code to no avail as my index stayed just a black canvas. This was frustrating, but in trying to look for resources outside of the p5 reference and coding lessons I did discover more p5 examples by Daniel Schiffman that looked helpful for other aspects of the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kelly and Diana were kind enough to show me how they made snow fall for their final week four daily, and I still wanted to learn how to make a falling rain daily. Scott was very generous with his time during office hours, and very thoroughly tried to explain some of the key variables concepts I have not been grasping. While the back and forth between his asking me questions as we went through my rain code and my frequently not knowing the answers was draining, I definitely felt that I made progress in our office hours meeting and Scott agreed. So like &lt;a href=&quot;http://tbreijak.github.io/blog/2016-02-17/Slow-and-Steady-Wins-the-Race.html&quot;&gt;Todd&lt;/a&gt;, I am feeling more hopeful that I am at least capable of learning the course concepts even if the process is long, difficult, and time-consuming. To be blunt, I hate math, computers, and lab classrooms. I particularly hate how all lab classrooms have the same soul-sucking fluorescent harsh lighting bulbs. While I am stressed out and frustrated with how behind I both am and feel in this course, I do feel that the time I put in today combined with Scott’s generous office hours assistance did help me learn. I’ve also though a lot this week about a professor I had at USF who always said that higher education should force students to step outside their comfort zone because otherwise they wouldn’t learn as much. I agree with this and on a cognitive level learning new skill sets and ways of thinking builds new paths in the mind more than just rehashing familiar knowledge. So as stressed as I am, I am going to continue to do my best and remind myself that I am learning more by stepping outside of my comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Open Lab Discouragement</title>
        <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io/blog/2016-02-17/Open-Lab-Discouragement.html</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Aigars Dzerviniks</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I am very glad to hear that &lt;a href=&quot;http://tbreijak.github.io/blog/2016-02-17/Slow-and-Steady-Wins-the-Race.html&quot;&gt;Todd&lt;/a&gt; left the private coding lesson we had with Scott on Monday feeling more confident because I left feeling the opposite. This was not Todd or Scott’s fault, but mine. At the open lab on Monday night, as Scott was going over the concepts of this week’s dailies with Todd, I realized how much of the coding and even the concepts behind the coding I had forgotten in the five days since I worked on the first three dailies (of this two week dailies set) last Wednesday. Kelly, Diana, and I had worked on the first three dailies together last Wednesday and figured out the first and third dailies quickly, and it felt great to figure those iterations out so swiftly. Sadly, I had forgotten much of the work we did and steps we took in the time we coded together on Wednesday and then Monday I really felt like I was starting from scratch with the 500 bubbles assignment even though I had already done it and should have been able to do it again from memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suffice this all to say that I have coded on my own for several of the dailies including my (awesome) turntable from the first week and my house which I refactored by myself, but I want and need to start doing even more coding on my own. Staring this week, I plan on dedicating my Fridays to just coding. I am still having trouble submitting work, which alone is inexcusable five weeks into the semester. Last week, I finally upgraded my laptop to El Capitan OS X so I could download Git Hub Desktop and work from home. Now, I can work in Atom and submit my dailies through Git Hub Desktop while working at home instead of only coding at the 9th floor lab or State Hall classroom. I’m so tired of doing coding and then cutting and pasting my code into my e-mail or transferring work to my USB thumb drive so that I could eventually put projects on my laptop. Honestly, just the thought of how full of sketches both my e-mail and thumb drive are stresses me out, and I wish I had just downloaded Git Hub Desktop sooner and started doing more alone time coding sooner. Ugh, I just realized I’ve been shaking my head as I type this post. Hopefully with the work I have been putting in and the added work I plan on doing I will be able to pass the class. I said last week that I was going to make more time to work with Scott during his office hours and I did do that this week so hopefully that is a sign that I’m capable of carrying through my strategies and goals for the course.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Manovich</title>
        <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io/blog/2016-02-17/Manovich.html</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Aigars Dzerviniks</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Lev Manovich’s The Language of New Media has been very helpful in clarifying what elements make up what we refer to as new media. My previous conception of what distinguished old and new media was limited to superficial analogies. I used to think that when I scanned my beloved David Bowie records into digital files I was clearly taking old or analog media (my physical records) and replicating them as new or digital media (mp3 files). David Silver, a professor at my undergraduate school, was all about the transformative power of Web 2.0 and users’ abilities to respond to and change web sites and programs, and I may have ended up misrepresenting Silver by thinking that new media is mainly defined by its interactive qualities (and Manovich calls interactive an “overused word” (228)). The town print newspaper would be old media while the openly changeable Wikipedia of Silver’s Web 2.0 would be new media (and I should clarify that Silver did not invent or even primarily popularize the phrase Web 2.0). Still, Manovich’s book clearly emphasizes that there is more to new media objects than their internal makeup of numbers and code. Why couldn’t I classify my digitized Bowie LPs and Silver’s broad Web 2.0 as new media and leave it at that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting farther into Manovich’s book and also chatting with Scott today, I understand that their composition of digital code is just one of the primary elements that classify new media objects. I find variability to be especially relevant. Manovich writes, “A new media object is not something fixed once or for all, but something that can exist in different, potentially infinite versions” (36). I mentioned to Scott that when DVDs first came out (and this might have been around the time Manovich was writing) a big part of their marketing push was a focus on ‘alternate angle’ options. Many of the movies released in the first wave of DVDs included alternate angles- angles that were shot and not used in the final film that viewers could access at different points by pressing the ‘angle’ button. This seemed like a form of variability where the viewer is able to interact with the film by varying the angles. When I told Scott this, he stressed that a blogging platform like WordPress or a social network like Facebook was even more productive for thinking about variability because they are databases and Manovich emphasizes the database in the world of new media. According to Scott, Facebook is one large database (that is also part of a larger database, the Web) where what is viewable varies by both users and devices. I’d also add that variability is also a part of Facebook because a user can decide what to post and remove on her account. So I have learned, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://tbreijak.github.io/blog/2016-02-17/Manovich-and-Haraway.html&quot;&gt;Todd&lt;/a&gt; alludes to in his post, that an object’s digital storage is just one aspect of it being new media.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Submitting Incompetence</title>
        <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io/blog/2016-02-10/Submitting-Incompetence.html</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Aigars Dzerviniks</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I will start my coding blog for this week by being frank and sharing that I am straight up embarrassed that I am still always unsure if I am submitting my dailies work correctly or not. &lt;a href=&quot;http://tbreijak.github.io/blog/2016-02-10/Another-Week-of-Coding.html&quot;&gt;Todd&lt;/a&gt; mentioned that he feels he is behind in the class on coding and the daily lessons, and to that I say, Todd, you are not alone. I’ve been doing our dailies, but I have not been consistently submitting them and I worry that this is putting me behind or at least on some kind of work slippery slope. I’ve been diligently doing my weekly assignments either on my own or with the assistance of David, Diana, and/or Kelly, but I am still always nervous when submitting a pull request. On a practical and reasonable level, I know that I shouldn’t be nervous about submitting a pull request because I both have notes on how to submit work and there is a ‘submitting work’ How To guide on the main Eng7006 GitHub page. Still, I get easily confused when I sometimes have multiple files in the same project, and then I start to worry that I’m not saving my work correctly and that I’m not going to submit the work correctly either, etc. Most of the time I have submitted my work I’ve had other people walk me through the process because I worry I’m going to do something wrong. At this point, it’s too far in the semester for me to not know how to submit work so I need to either stop worrying when I submit a pull request or at least realize that my worrying is what is distracting me from just knowing how to do the same process each time I submit my work when I already have instructions on how to do so in my notes and the How To page. In a previous blog post, I mentioned that I want to take advantage of Scott’s office hours for help on matters like this, but I still have not done this and want to make the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that made thinking through this week’s dailies more constructive than other weeks is that the daily work we had done in previous weeks was helpful both in terms of writing out the code and thinking about what needed to be included or excluded from the code. For example, to keep the bubbles from collecting at the top, I thought back to the OG, rudimentary vertical and horizontal balls and how originally they didn’t bounce. That put me on track to being able to envision both on the canvas and within the code what the final product would look like, and this led to that particular daily being done quickly. I was pleased with this week’s dailies that I could use what I have learned in thinking through the coding, and being able to do this was a reminder that I have been learning even though I find the coding process to be both mentally and time draining.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Haraway</title>
        <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io/blog/2016-02-10/Haraway.html</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Aigars Dzerviniks</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Like a father figure who has influenced his children’s thinking even though they give him short shrift when they elucidate ideas that eerily sound like ones that came from his mouth, Marshall McLuhan seems to inspire Donna Haraway’s thinking in a “A Cyborg Manifesto” even though Haraway doesn’t directly refer to McLuhan. I was happy to see that in his blog post this week, &lt;a href=&quot;http://joetorok.github.io/blog/2016-02-10/haraway-and-cyborgs.html&quot;&gt;Joe&lt;/a&gt; also caught the ‘McLuhanian’ nature of Haraway’s chapter. McLuhan’s prescient thinking seems applicable to any instances where Haraway even alludes to technology becoming an extension of humans, let alone technology and humans forming into a hybrid cyborg identity. McLuhan believed that technology became an extension of us partially in how it conditioned our lives and how we think. He felt that we become so dependent on certain technological tools that they become deeply connected to us and we feel the lack when we do not have these tools. Now, medical technology is so advanced that humans can replace missing body parts with technological body parts. Haraway writes, “For us, in imagination and in other practice, machines can be prosthetic devices, intimate components, friendly selves” (314). An abstract example of this is the feelings of incompleteness I feel when I don’t have my electronic fitness tracker on to tell me how many steps I’ve walked or what time it is. More concretely, prosthetics and artificial limbs today are can be technologically advanced creations, and on this superficial level humans with robotic limbs or extremities fulfill the cyborg-human hybrid at least physically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a completely different note from McLuhan, much of Haraway’s tracing and analysis of the homework economy seemed clearly connectable to the effects of neoliberalism. As the capitalist class and the accumulation of capital for it is prioritized above all else, neoliberalism brings about many (if not all) of the effects that Haraway mentions in her description of the disapora, including “urban homelessness,… surveillance systems through electronics funds transfer,… international restructuring of the working classes, … development of new time arrangements to facilitate the homework economy,… continued erosion of the welfare state” (308) and so on. The way Haraway describes the ‘informatics of domination’ as “a massive intensification of insecurity and cultural impoverishment, with common failure of subsistence networks for the most vulnerable” (309) could also be the most appropriate way to articulate the intentions and consequences of neoliberalism. While neoliberalism can take on different meanings depending on who is using the term, technology seems to play a crucial role in how neoliberalism is both articulated and disseminated.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Second Lab Post</title>
        <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io/blog/2016-02-03/Second-Lab-Post.html</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Aigars Dzerviniks</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My coding experience continues to move in waves of deep frustration and childlike elation. I was able to post my reading blog post just fine last Thursday afternoon, but on Thursday night at 10:30 pm or so I posted my lab blog post the exact same way only to receive multiple e-mails from GitHub reading ‘Page Build Error’ without any explanation as to what the error was or how I could fix it. I e-mailed Scott about this and he was very understanding, and I also e-mailed GitHub directly who got back to me six hours later. At the open lab, Scott tried to fix my blog based on what GitHub’s help department had told me the error was, but GitHub was wrong so Scott emptied my blog so we could start from scratch. After he did this, my blog wouldn’t come up at all, and I was especially frustrated and disappointed that I had done my work only to not be able to post it. I felt like someone in the situation of the slacker despite not slacking off at all on the reading or writing. Scott was even ready to throw in the towel and contact GitHub himself when David miraculously saw that one line of code in my config.yml was missing my username. I hadn’t touched this since we originally set it up in class so I have no idea why my username was absent from a single line of code in the config.yml. Fortunately, once I put my username back in, my blog was up and I could post just fine. I am grateful to both Scott and David for helping me with this aggravating situation, and I hope I never experience this issue again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dianarosenberger.github.io/blog/2016-02-03/week3.html&quot;&gt;Diana&lt;/a&gt; mentioned in her coding post for this week that working with other classmates on these projects is a soothing and constructive benefit in the midst of what is often a stressful and confusing activity. I know a few acquaintances who are professional engineers, and they all speak of getting tunnel vision on their projects where they get so focused on one aspect of something they are working on that they can’t see other mistakes right in front of them. Probably every person in our class experiences that when they are working on the dailies. The nice thing about working with other people on the coding assignments is that one person might think to check something that the other person or people didn’t think to do. Kelly, Diana, and I worked on our dailies today, and at several points when we were stuck and our work wouldn’t come up in Chrome I had us double check the JavaScript console and sure enough each time we had some kind of error in it. For me, being able to contribute something is a rewarding feeling, and it lets me know that I am learning even if the process feels slow and draining.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Kittler</title>
        <link>http://AdenJ86.github.io/blog/2016-02-03/Kittler.html</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <author>Aigars Dzerviniks</author>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As I was reading Friedrich A. Kittler’s Gramophone, Film Typewriter, Marshall McLuhan’s notion of technology becoming an extension of man kept coming to mind. Early in “Gramophone” while recounting the development of the phonograph, Kittler writes, “A telegraph as an artificial mouth, a telephone as an artificial ear- the stage was set for the phonograph. Functions of the central nervous system had been technologically implemented” (28). Just as McLuhan wrote of the clock becoming an extension of man through its ubiquity in the literate world and man’s dependence on it and use of eyes and sight for telling time; the telegraph, the telephone, and phonograph were also influenced by sense organs and then became extensions of these organs and senses. In her blog post this week, &lt;a href=&quot;http://kellypolasek.github.io/blog/2016-02-03/Reading-Kittler&#39;s-Gramophone.html&quot;&gt;Kelly&lt;/a&gt; also caught the common ground between McLuhan and Kittler on machines affecting our senses and sensory organs and also becoming those very organs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McLuhan believed that technology became such a profoundly ingrained part of us that its influence could be considered wired into and extending our central nervous system. As I wrote in my blog last week, McLuhan emphasizes the significance of this idea through the very subtitle of Understanding Media: The Extensions of Man. There are even a few instances in Kittler which seem to allude to McLuhan’s specific thinking on technology and the central nervous system including, “Artificial mouths and ears… as technological implementations of the central nervous system” (28) and “In order to implement technologically (and thus render superfluous) the functions of the central nervous system, it first had to be reconstructed” (74). Kittler also mentions Otto Wiener’s inaugural lecture on “‘the extension of our senses’ by instruments” (77). Repeatedly in his text, Kittler returns to McLuhan’s concepts that technology becomes extensions of man and profoundly connected to him, but he doesn’t repeatedly mention McLuhan despite how much his thinking and research seems to defer to McLuhan.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    

  </channel>
</rss>
